[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't need to be a specific theme, though.
[SPEAKER_01]: The whole point is to, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: I think it was what you said a few days ago, when we spoke about how different people take different, eh... approach to practice, and then, how some people's approach involves forsaking clarity.
Hm.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you... if you're sort of craving for clarity of understanding, they would say they're just craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, eh... and by doing so, dismiss
[SPEAKER_01]: There is absolutely no other method.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, there is no method that you could prescribe
[SPEAKER_01]: They can then result automatically in clarity.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only way to arrive at it is to keep investigating and digging in, digging out for the meaning.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what the suttas mean when they talk about dealt with a knife and then just keep digging, keep cutting, until you reach the clarity of understanding of certain universal truths.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why we spoke about the idea of... well, how it was in the suttas, you know, when...
[SPEAKER_01]: Somebody declares, even if they don't necessarily declare their knowledge, if they have a level of understanding of dhamma, like, you know, if they meet with the monks, they'll be interrogating each other, not for the sake of argument, or for the sake of, um, oh, I know more than you do.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was really just to test their own understanding and see if there is anything that they haven't considered, because of which they're maybe not getting the full picture.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no understanding that, that, uh, needs to, needs to be developed.
[SPEAKER_01]: So the interrogation basically is done for the sake of clarity.
[SPEAKER_01]: Testing your own clarity, testing clarity of others, increasing your own clarity.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even like, for example, even in cases like Arya Savakas, who already don't need anyone for their own clarity.
[SPEAKER_01]: If they end up talking dhamma to others, it makes them think about dhamma, which means, makes them develop those principles more and more and more.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's a win-win, really.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, eh... the reason why you won't see that done today is because, well, it requires some degree of understanding to start with.
[SPEAKER_01]: Otherwise, you just put together bouncing ideas of each other, and that cannot possibly result in the knowledge.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's kind of ironic, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_00]: People think, before they go to monasteries, they think that monasteries can be a place where people do investigate, where they have discussions together, and they go to the monastery, and then they sort of spend a bit of time, then they go to...
[SPEAKER_00]: When do you have these meetings?
[SPEAKER_00]: When you discuss things?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, and then the meetings that are there are kind of a sutta study group, which is basically just a presentation of information, and then we all chip in with our opinion and review on a certain topic.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's really not like, okay, what does this mean?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if we encounter a contradiction, well, that must be resolved.
[SPEAKER_01]: But often, I remember, you know, people say, oh, well, I read this sutra and it means like this, like this, and then you would point out that there are other sutras that would contradict their understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not for the sake of, like, personally attacking somebody, but pointing out that that cannot be the universal principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it's for the sake of your own clarity and your own understanding, you mustn't stop until there is at least sufficient level of that clarity and time.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't mean you won't find contradictions later on, but certainly, if you're aware that they are, you must make the work to undo them.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that is literally the most direct way you can have towards gaining the right view and understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's undoing your wrong views through self-questioning,
[SPEAKER_01]: You're looking for the meaning of the universal phenomena in your experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I crossed my mind to, eh... well, we can be asking each other, eh... action, nature of action.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, like, obviously, we talk about it all the time, and it seems to be the convergence point for wholesome and unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there are obviously many, many views associated with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, eh... people inevitably have to start with the wrong views.
[SPEAKER_01]: But becoming aware of the wrong views as your starting point, helps you then make the effort towards undoing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not gonna...
[SPEAKER_01]: There's an assumption that you'll find the right view, when you sort of go beyond your wrong views.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I'm...
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm affected with the wrong views, so I just need to keep looking for the right answers, and then I'll get the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right view is basically undoing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your views that are wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how you arrive at the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there's absolutely... it's inconceivable that those wrong views would be undone on its own, without the effort of actually unscrewing them, and making them fade away.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the repetitive effort everybody talks about, and the gradual shelving of the ocean, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to keep applying that pressure and effort towards your own wrong views, and that's how you'll undo them.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why they're irreversible as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: Once you undo them, you can't, like, reacquire them.
[SPEAKER_01]: But there's this common notion of, oh, I just do these observances, methods, techniques, practices, and then I'll have a magical experience of the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, interrogation, action.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: What is... where is action constituted?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it in... say you're about to do something, physically.
[SPEAKER_03]: Go for a walk, using your body for walking.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is that action in your physical movements?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or is that action in the decision to walk, even before you start walking?
[SPEAKER_02]: And when does the action begin?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you can say that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, the thing begins... You say a plant doesn't begin when it starts to grow outside the soil.
[SPEAKER_02]: It begins at its roots.
[SPEAKER_02]: You know, it begins there, where it's rooted.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's where it grows from.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you intend to
[SPEAKER_02]: If you decide to walk outside, and then you start walking, that walking is secondary.
[SPEAKER_01]: The walking is secondary to what?
[SPEAKER_01]: To the decision.
[SPEAKER_01]: To the decision to walk.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, it's secondary in terms of it's... it's more... it's more grown.
[SPEAKER_02]: It proliferates.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it sort of starts...
[SPEAKER_00]: It starts with...
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, I sort of see it as, like, there's a... basically, there's this possibility for going for a walk.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's this, like... even before a decision is made, there's this... that's a possibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what does start with that possibility?
[SPEAKER_00]: You say, you see, it starts with that.
[SPEAKER_00]: What... what starts with that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Not... not starts, but, like... so...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, action is like... there are these possibilities and that one possibility of going for a walk presents itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it may just be kind of bodily.
[SPEAKER_00]: You may not even...
[SPEAKER_00]: But is that an action?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is that an action, then?
[SPEAKER_00]: I guess not unless, yeah, if you don't, if you don't choose that possibility, then no.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you choose that possibility, but also... Because that's, that's what the question is, was.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, what's action?
[SPEAKER_01]: Where, where does the question, where does the action start?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then there can be no action without choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Correct.
[SPEAKER_01]: All of what you said is correct.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: You couldn't choose to act in a certain manner, if that's not given as a possibility.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're a wheelchair-bound, you can't use your legs, and the possibility of walking has been permanently removed.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, that's the important point.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's not where the action starts.
[SPEAKER_01]: And sometimes people, not necessarily differentiating that, ends up blaming possibilities and things that just arise in their mind on the level of possibilities, and they assume them to be the actions, and try to get rid of it all.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, there is no... Action to walk, or rather choice to walk, is not the action.
[SPEAKER_01]: The actual walking would be action of walking, which you maintain,
[SPEAKER_01]: So, action without choice is inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why we say every action is intention.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, intention to walk, the choice that you made, the intention that's present, hence you are walking while that choice is present.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's another thing, how people will just jump into the assumption that the whole thing is linear.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you made a choice and that choice has ended when you started walking.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's absolutely not the case.
[SPEAKER_01]: The intention remains there.
[SPEAKER_01]: It gives the intelligibility to every single step you make.
[SPEAKER_01]: You wouldn't know what to do next if you had no knowledge of walking, no intention to walk.
[SPEAKER_01]: You would just set the foot forward and then, oh, what do I do now?
[SPEAKER_01]: But you already know that walking involves moving forward, using your limbs.
[SPEAKER_00]: But people would also tend to think that the choice is
[SPEAKER_00]: A kind of explicit, ah, now I'll do this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's that's a topic in itself as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, like, extra volitional or something like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you, so, so, if you don't, but then there are occasions when you realize that you're doing something, and I didn't actually explicitly, in awareness, go, I'll stop, I'll do this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, then, actually, that's where I must have just missed it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It must have been there, but I must have just missed this.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, where does awareness of the choice come in, then?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is why the whole, like, wakefulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, see, the... what you said now, it's where people start with, in terms of their view.
[SPEAKER_01]: They think, okay, so, only when I'm super extra mindful, that I made a choice, that's a mindful choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything below that threshold of super-extra-mindfulness doesn't constitute a choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I just must always remain equally mindful to this, like, overloading extent of I'm moving, I'm moving, I'm touching, I want to drink, I'm drinking, I'm sitting.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if I, if I, if I find myself doing something and I didn't actually remember... Means I lost my mind for a second.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: I've done something wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's unsustainable.
[SPEAKER_01]: That kind of practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is, incidentally, kind of the contemporary take on mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, therefore, basically, we are constantly making choices without actually being aware at the time of doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, there are sub...
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, so that's the point that I was going to make.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the key to practice mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not to tailor your choices to your assumed degree of mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's to refine your mindfulness to actually discern the choices that are already there and being made.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's completely the opposite direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that takes much more work.
[SPEAKER_01]: Refining your discernment of the choices that they're enduring, because you're doing all these actions, as opposed to just sweep all that away, and now only what counts is what I decision, full-on, mindful presence of my every moment, what I decide, what I intend.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you always have to lapse from that kind of state.
[SPEAKER_01]: But instead of trying to fit your choices into mindfulness, you refine your mindfulness to start seeing all these choices that are there on their own.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how you also get to a prudence as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why there's... and the confusion is basically because it's hard to understand that if you're unaware of a choice, it doesn't mean it was unintentional.
[SPEAKER_01]: It means simply your mind is so far removed from your self-awareness.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why then people say, okay, so I must make only intentional choices that count.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you start with that, but you actually want to refine your mindfulness then further and further to see other, slightly less intentional, but still on the level of, on the threshold of intention, choices that you're making.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how would you then, for example, you, how would you then, for example, practice mindfulness practically?
[SPEAKER_01]: How would you, how would you be mindful?
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, no right or wrong answer.
[SPEAKER_01]: Describe how you understand it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, whatever understanding a person has, even if they don't have the fundamental understanding, it's a form of understanding for them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the practice, then, is to refine that understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: Get freed from contradictions or mistakes, and then take it further in that direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not like, that's wrong, here is the right answer.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, from that point of view, there's no wrong answer, really.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just accurate and less accurate.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you want to go about, during the day, practice mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: How would you do?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, I come and ask you, how can I be mindful for... throughout the day?
[SPEAKER_01]: How would you, eh... advise me?
[SPEAKER_01]: What can I do?
[SPEAKER_03]: Paying attention to the things that are already sort of happening.
[SPEAKER_01]: Such as?
[SPEAKER_01]: What do you mean?
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't understand that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like right now, I'm sitting.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like you said, I don't have to always keep thinking, I'm sitting, I'm sitting, I'm sitting.
[SPEAKER_03]: But I do intend to sit.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, there's a... there's a degree of awareness, even if I'm not fully attending to that I'm sitting.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how is that then... what do you mean by paying attention to that?
[SPEAKER_01]: What do you... what do you say, paying attention to that?
[SPEAKER_01]: What... what... what...
[SPEAKER_03]: It's more like reminding yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of?
[SPEAKER_03]: Of... that already, like, whatever degree of awareness is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of what?
[SPEAKER_03]: Things that are already there, whether it's your bodily posture or...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how often do I have to remind myself that, in order to maintain mindfulness?
[SPEAKER_03]: It depends how often you, sort of, drift away from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, every time one would drift away, as soon as they remember, they need to remind themself?
[SPEAKER_03]: I suppose, if you can just, like, think of it as, like, I'm drifting away, that you already know that you're drifting away, sort of a thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the act of reminding yourself, what would that entail?
[SPEAKER_00]: Say, you remember that you forgot.
[SPEAKER_01]: Where would now that act of reminding, where do I aim it?
[SPEAKER_01]: What do I remind myself of?
[SPEAKER_03]: What am I doing right now?
[SPEAKER_03]: What am I thinking right now?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the present actions, whatever those might be.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, can you say then that... can there be mindfulness without actions?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, more accurately, there can be no mindfulness without intentional basis.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even if you're restraining a physical action, there is an intentional basis to act.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why everything would come down, then, to discerning whether it's rooted in wholesome or unwholesome, those intentions.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it's unwholesome, you don't allow the act to take place by body, speech or mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's all the satipaṭṭhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: He knows his mind is affected with lust.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, as a rule of thumb, yeah, try and remind yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: But not of some kind of, oh, be here now in the present moment,
[SPEAKER_01]: But remind yourself of what is your present situation that you forgot about, which then means you can start reminding yourself of the fact that you just forgot.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when you remember that you lapsed, that's what you remind yourself of.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ah, there is the experience of forgetting right now, because I forgot.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you stop focusing then so much on the content of what you forgot.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, I forgot that I'm sitting.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're still seated.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you clearly haven't forgotten completely, because otherwise you would have stood up
[SPEAKER_00]: But that intention is still there, because the body is still doing it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, could you say, by... if you, say, lose the context of your situation, you stop being mindful, you forget what you're doing, you just look at... you can ask yourself, what are the roots of what I'm doing?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's another thing, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if you are careless in regard to your intentions, you'll be intending upon intentions, and you'll be doing six different things at once.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, that doesn't matter that you can't handle doing six different things at once, but they must be then unified with one general intention.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, sometimes you can actually, if you don't have clarity of your intentions, you can re-clarify them by seeing what you're doing, seeing what is the general context of all these different things that I'm doing, and then allow that to maintain in your mind as a thought that endures on its own.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, why am I sitting here, right now?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, why am I sitting right here?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, actions are always sort of hierarchical?
[SPEAKER_01]: They are, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can always... you can sort of focus on a particular, you know, I don't know, I'm...
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm...
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm lifting the cup, I'm pouring the... Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or you go, and I'm just making coffee.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't need to worry about the... Every particular little movement.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that is also why people who... who just start their practice, who don't necessarily know, and who would be focusing on every moment, that's where they do get some sort of release through that, like, it does feel like you're mindful, certainly more mindful than usual.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you're aware of the action you're doing, the intention, that it's simultaneously present, that is implicit.
[SPEAKER_01]: But see, the problem is, if you don't know that you're supposed to be looking beyond the action you're doing and discern the present intention in your mind, then you'll just become a mechanical robot who tries to sort of touching, touching, moving, pouring, pouring, lifting, lifting.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you...
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you refuse to look what's underneath.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you think, I must just look at the surface of these acts.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's why, initially, there is a degree of like, oh, yeah, this feels like it works.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you are, in a generic way, you are implying the awareness of your intention to do this.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, things will get complex, things will get faster, harder to control, and your mindfulness is gone with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that would not happen if you remain mindful of the intention to make coffee.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't matter how quickly, how slowly you do it, you are making coffee.
[SPEAKER_01]: And until that's fulfilled, all of your actions will be around that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, yeah, it's... you're being mindful of your intention, you're being mindful of the context of your actions, your... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of all particular... What did you call it before?
[SPEAKER_00]: The root, or the...
[SPEAKER_00]: The root, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: The root of your...
[SPEAKER_00]: The root of the particular things that you're doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's all...
[SPEAKER_01]: Even the root of your own...
[SPEAKER_01]: The root of your own attention.
[SPEAKER_01]: Attending to the cup, attending to the coffee.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's all rooted in intention to fulfill this goal of making a cup of coffee.
[SPEAKER_00]: I want a cup of coffee.
[SPEAKER_01]: Singleness of that context.
[SPEAKER_01]: Singleness of that purpose.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not singleness of every aspect of your act.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like when...
[SPEAKER_00]: When people go on meditation retreats and do some kind of... they'll be very careful about, I don't know, sensations in the nostrils or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I was thinking...
[SPEAKER_00]: I think for a lot of people, mindfulness is about like going on a retreat and, you know, sitting in a room together and focusing your attention on your nostrils or your breathing or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: And
[SPEAKER_00]: People get so absorbed in that, but they completely forget the fact that they have chosen to go on this retreat for whatever reason, and everything that they're doing is determined by that more general intention.
[SPEAKER_01]: Would you be able to do any of those things...
[SPEAKER_00]: Without that more general intention?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, no, no, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: Would you be able to do any of those things without implicit belief that somehow doing those things will fulfill your goal and purpose?
[SPEAKER_02]: Through a particular act of attending to my breath, the roots of my act, which might be unwholesome, based on greed, hate and delusion, through attending my breath, that general intention, where everything is rooted,
[SPEAKER_02]: And even if a person does not necessarily explicitly think this,
[SPEAKER_01]: The fact is that you start with, like, I don't know, what am I supposed to do, and then you choose to do this, out of that lack of knowledge, you already... well, you manufacture the belief that what you are about to do might possibly result in uprooting, basically, the roots of your actions in the first place.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, like what you just said now.
[SPEAKER_02]: Is it uprooting?
[SPEAKER_02]: Or am I just putting on top?
[SPEAKER_02]: Piling up.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you're not even addressing that more general... No.
[SPEAKER_01]: And no amount of practice points you towards addressing it either.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: The practice that you would be learning in the retreat center would be you do this, you do this, you do this.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's absolutely no point in any... like, wait, you stop and look at the intentions of your actions.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you jumped into it out of a belief, which then automatically, simultaneously fabricated that implication that
[SPEAKER_01]: This might work and help me.
[SPEAKER_01]: And now everything is based on that magical connection of doing random acts and believing that enlightenment will happen to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, mindfulness of action is gonna... somehow needs to involve a recognition of this distinction between general and particular.
[SPEAKER_01]: And... Well, how would you... how would you do that on a more practical level?
[SPEAKER_00]: For yourself, for example.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, to... you know, you recognize... you can recognize... just asking yourself, why am I doing this?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there's these particular things that I'm doing, but you can just question to... but what... why am I doing this?
[SPEAKER_00]: What's more gen... what... what... like... you said before, you're sitting down, but you're... why am I here?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why am I sitting here?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why am I in...?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: And exactly, you can see that simply... Why am I living in Sri Lanka?
[SPEAKER_01]: Simply through questioning like that, you will also then be looking at the
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, developing knowledge in regard to your own actions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why am I doing this?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can sometimes say, why am I doing this?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, well, because such and such thing happened to myself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but why did I choose that those things be the reason for my action right here, right now?
[SPEAKER_01]: It always comes back on you.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if... if my... the weight of my attention
[SPEAKER_02]: is placed on the roots of my act.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not that you forget about your act, but the... this might be wrong, but the weight of my attention is not solely placed on my act, but on the roots.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, it makes sure... it does... it makes sure that the
[SPEAKER_02]: The acts that I do, the more particular acts I do, are always in line with that intention.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how do you...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I don't have to worry about what act I'm doing, because it's being driven by this intention that I have, which I'm maintaining by...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how do you place the weight of your attention onto the root of the attention?
[SPEAKER_01]: How do you do that?
[SPEAKER_02]: How can one do that?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, as I said at the end, I said now...
[SPEAKER_02]: I think it's the same question.
[SPEAKER_02]: How can I maintain awareness of my intention, so that all my actions are driven by that?
[SPEAKER_00]: At the root, you mean?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how can you maintain that recognition of the motivation of all these particular... Is that the same question?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how do you do it?
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I'm asking.
[SPEAKER_02]: You've got to learn how to, you know, what the context is of your action.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, how to do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, can you give an example of a context in regard to the action?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if somebody was listening to it for the first time, would know like, okay, that's where I go to look for this.
[SPEAKER_01]: What would be the practical situation?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, can I, I don't know, give an example of what's happening right now?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, okay, go ahead.
[SPEAKER_01]: Describe it on the basis of an example.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if I, if my intent, say my intention, why am I sitting here?
[SPEAKER_02]: My intention is to uncover my wrong understandings.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, why do I, why am I doing that?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I'm freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: Can I ask further?
[SPEAKER_02]: What's the first next question?
[SPEAKER_02]: What's my intention to be free from suffering?
[SPEAKER_02]: To be... to be unbothered.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is... what is bothering?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, it's suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you want to be free from suffering, because you don't want to suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's how you know how you can't ask any further.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: The question closes upon itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you are then...
[SPEAKER_02]: If that's the... that's the context of my actions,
[SPEAKER_02]: The reason why I'm a monk, the reason why I'm sitting here, the reason why I'm eating, staying alive, breathing, and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's because you don't like suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, I'm trying to... yeah, I don't want to suffer.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, I don't like suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: All the suffering bothers you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's a topic in itself, but before we go into that, so how do you then do it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Back onto what you said.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I have to...
[SPEAKER_01]: Without ceasing to do what you're doing...
[SPEAKER_02]: I have to remember that.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you're asking how to remember.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, I'm asking what... what to remember in order to maintain the mindfulness of your particular actions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you were talking about shifting the weight onto the root of your attention, which means that which you're attending, you want to shift some weight from it onto where, and I'm asking how.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not necessarily why, which is because you want to be free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: How do you go about it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, well, automatically I want to talk about, you know, yoniso, manasikāra.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, because this is what it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm trying to not... Yeah, no, I just feel like, if, again, saying what I asked Aruna, if I want to learn, how would you tell me practically how can I do that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, what is the theme?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what you're basically saying is, if you don't forget the motive behind your own presently enduring action, you are dividing the weight or shifting some weight back at the origin of
[SPEAKER_01]: What you're attending in front of you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Isn't it just the process of asking yourself, why am I doing this?
[SPEAKER_00]: You would start with that, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, why am I doing this?
[SPEAKER_00]: Just asking that question.
[SPEAKER_01]: A recognition of why you're doing it and what you're doing right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, like, I'm sitting here and talking or like I'm going for a walk.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, everything, sure, everything will be funneled into the most general purpose.
[SPEAKER_01]: I am a monk, I will be free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that might be a bit too far removed for somebody when they just start.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you want to find slightly less general basis for your act.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, why am I going for this walk?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because I haven't moved my body for three days.
[SPEAKER_01]: I was sick, so I need to move.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, that's your motivation.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you say, is there anything wrong with that motivation?
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I can go for a walk.
[SPEAKER_01]: Where do I go for a walk and so on?
[SPEAKER_01]: That's another thing you should be considering then.
[SPEAKER_01]: If exactly, sometimes, oh, because I'm kind of bored and restless in my kuti, like, oh, so I am acting out of unwholesome basis of restlessness.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, simply questioning yourself about the motive.
[SPEAKER_01]: Where is your action that you're about to do, or you have been doing, if you caught yourself at the later stage, where is it rooted?
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's all you need to do in order to clarify the situation.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't need to every time arrive at the answer that because you want to be free from suffering and you're a monk.
[SPEAKER_01]: Although, that's going to become implied.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but... Because see, like now, oh, I want to avoid acting out of ill-will.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, because from the other point of view, that's unwholesome and that prevents the fulfillment of my goal of being a monk and being free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: But on a practical basis, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why am I doing what I'm doing right now?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, because of this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Simply maintaining the knowledge of why you're doing whatever you're doing, that's your mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is basically beginning and the ending of mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you have to maintain your knowledge, but you have to question.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, you question your motives, question your motives.
[SPEAKER_02]: That generates the knowledge.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm just thinking, is there a danger that some people, when you ask yourself, why am I doing this?
[SPEAKER_01]: There's a danger to psychologize.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's what I mean, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or even, you just come up with some
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why I keep insisting you have to find motivation.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not about finding the answer, necessarily, inasmuch as it's finding the motivation, which is then the answer.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why am I doing this?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because
[SPEAKER_01]: My parents never loved me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's not a motivation.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's you chose that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why did you choose that to be a reason?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because other people have parents that don't love them and they don't do the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why did you make these choices?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is a danger of psychologizing in as much as there is a danger, if you don't do it at all, of completely ignoring it and just following the mechanical, methodical practice of a robotic technique.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, yeah, even if you start psychologizing, you ask yourself that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, why am I now providing all these explanations for this?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's asking why and... but also taking responsibility for... Well, discerning the responsibility that's there, that you can't have no... have no choice but to have.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, eh...
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, having the knowledge of the motivation
[SPEAKER_02]: Attentions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Behind things you attend, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Knowledge of the roots of your attention.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that also then means, brings us back to all the talks we've been doing before about peripheral awareness and so on, means you can't attend, on the same level, the knowledge because of which you're attending all these personal, particular things.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why you can't, or rather, if you do start attending to that knowledge,
[SPEAKER_01]: As if it is an object of your attention, means then you're motivated by something else.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you need to discern motivation without needing to attend to it at the expense of everything else.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why mindfulness will result in knowledge.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's what knowledge is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Keeping things in the back of your mind that you already know without having to think about them all the time.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's exactly what knowledge is.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you don't know something, you have to think and attend and try to figure it out.
[SPEAKER_01]: Once you do, automatically, it recedes into the background and becomes the significance of your experience, whatever you want to call it.
[SPEAKER_01]: The point is, you don't have to be going around thinking that 2 and 2 is 4, 2 and 2 is 4, 2 and 2 is 4, because you already know.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you know what?
[SPEAKER_01]: You know how to add things up.
[SPEAKER_01]: You understood the principle of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're not thinking about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the point here, to understand the principles of, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: Anicca.
[SPEAKER_01]: Understand the principle of dukkha.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it all revolves around the sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, having non-mindfulness of these things involves the self-view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Having mindfulness of these things uproots the self-view, because it makes it redundant.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you mean, like, so somebody who... someone who can drive, doesn't have to think about driving.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, and they can't think about the driving, see?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because they don't know how to drive.
[SPEAKER_01]: They can think about how to move the stick, how to twist the wheel, how to press the pedal.
[SPEAKER_01]: When they understand, as in develop more general understanding of these particular actions, that's when they know how to drive.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then all they think about is driving.
[SPEAKER_01]: They don't think about every particular movement of the hand.
[SPEAKER_01]: But see, it's like people... when people... people act normally like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then they get into practice and then they try to undo this and become focused on every little thing you do, at the expense of what you're doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's what you were led to believe, that that's what meditation is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Moment to moment experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ignoring the bigger picture, which is already a moment experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why I keep saying, like before, I remember, you know, the one-pointedness.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's how people, like, refer to samādhi.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it is...
[SPEAKER_01]: Two ways you can go about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It can be one-pointedness, in terms of you focusing on one point so hard, that you forget about everything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: You become absorbed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, you discern one point that includes all these other things within it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, which one does it sound better?
[SPEAKER_01]: Focusing hard on one little instance, so I simply have no recognition of any other instances.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, finding the fundamental instance that already includes all of these instances.
[SPEAKER_01]: And given that the Buddha gave so many similes... examples and similes of a gatekeeper, you don't go chase around every individual instance of a person in the city, you stand at the gate, you know they're inside, that's all you need to know.
[SPEAKER_01]: I have a knowledge that all these people are in.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's samādhi.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's harder to do, because you have to question yourself, and that will bring anxiety, that will bring doubt, that will be... and that's exactly why the five hindrances then become such a thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's manifested through... through proper practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if I just tell you, you know, just focus on your nostrils, focus on touching with soles of your feet, as if walking means I want to touch things with my soles.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Walking means I want to move, I want to walk.
[SPEAKER_01]: All these other particular actions you can look at, will be seen correctly only if you don't forget the general context of your intention to walk, that persists for the duration of your act of walking.
[SPEAKER_00]: And again, it's that principle of the whole and the part.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can only understand what part is,
[SPEAKER_00]: From the context of the whole, you can't understand the part, you know.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like the part, you understand the part, then you put together to get the whole.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the other way around.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to start with the whole to understand what the part is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And even if sometimes you don't know what the whole is,
[SPEAKER_01]: The fact that you're assembling parts to find the hole, means you only have a recognition that there must be a hole to these parts.
[SPEAKER_01]: But what people hope is that there's absolutely zero knowledge of a hole, and somehow I'll magically arrive at the knowledge of a hole based on these random parts I'm doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's why, yes, being instructed, hearing the dhamma, as in getting the sense of the context that must be developed, does give the direction to all those individual actions.
[SPEAKER_01]: But how individual those actions will become,
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that depends how wrong your views are.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you can't say, oh, well, becoming a monk and wearing robes and eating once a day.
[SPEAKER_01]: All of those are individual actions towards your practice of freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: But they're not on the same level as individual actions of touching, touching, moving, moving, sitting, sitting, feeling, thinking, thinking, speaking, speaking, sleeping, sleeping.
[SPEAKER_01]: Those are also individual actions.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you see how much more they're misguided.
[SPEAKER_01]: They are misguided.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the more you commit to it, the further away from the context you drift.
[SPEAKER_01]: And exactly that can happen to monks as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: When being a monk becomes about having my perfect robe, perfect stitch.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm such a beautiful disciple.
[SPEAKER_01]: I always put Ajahn's cloth perfectly and I walk so softly, I speak so softly.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I'm a layman still, mentally, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: So,
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: All these are individual actions, but it's whether you know that you're supposed to look for the context behind them or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's rather... That's when you become like a career monk, when it's about appearance, it's about this, it's about serving and do this, and not about understanding the context of your actions, the context of the suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's kind of easier to obsess over the...
[SPEAKER_01]: It is.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why Sīla Bhārata Paramārtha is the first fetter.
[SPEAKER_01]: People derogatory sort of...
[SPEAKER_01]: derogatorily translated as as rites and rituals, because, you know, nobody's silly enough to worship rites and rituals as a as a vehicle to enlightenment.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it isn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sīlavāta paramāsa means virtue and duty.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, me doing the virtue, doing the duty, without understanding the context of it, means I'm fettered by things I'm doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, imagine you take that even further, and I start doing all these mindless meditation techniques and everything else.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, literally, you basically completely cement any access to the direction where the context of your actions are.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, your context, your motivation, will govern your actions.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you protect...
[SPEAKER_02]: It always does.
[SPEAKER_02]: ...that higher mind, that higher motivation, that big context, with your life,
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't have to worry about much else.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's like...
[SPEAKER_02]: Absolutely.
[SPEAKER_02]: ...that you get... you have to learn how to drive before you can get there.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, what is... what is it...
[SPEAKER_02]: I want to develop kindness, loving kindness.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I must get...
[SPEAKER_02]: I must get used to what kind things are, pick up the theme of kindness, and then hold... and then make that...
[SPEAKER_02]: Develop the theme.
[SPEAKER_02]: ...as the thing that I'm... my... my shining light in my life is that context, that... that sign of kindness.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what I concentrate on.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what I compose my life in, all around.
[SPEAKER_01]: Without needing to sort of go through, like, daily repetition of particular actions, of expressing kindness to everyone...
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't do... ...smiling and doing all these things.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Kindness means absence of your will.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you will be naturally doing things.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because that's where they're rooted.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if that's the theme of your... of the game, is kindness, then whatever I come into contact with, which I...
[SPEAKER_02]: I will come into contact with things, because I'm eating, I'm going to the toilet, I'm speaking with people, so I'm getting sick.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if... it doesn't matter what things you come across and against, if a backdrop against those things is the theme that you invested effort in developing, the theme of kindness, no ill will can seep into these particular actions, because they're at a lower level.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, pretty fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you are unclear about the theme of kindness,
[SPEAKER_01]: Lack of clarity will then give rise to what?
[SPEAKER_01]: Lust, aversion, delusion, ignorance.
[SPEAKER_02]: Always gives rise to these things.
[SPEAKER_02]: A painful thing comes up, like an annoying thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it will test your clarity of the theme of kindness.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, someone starts to insult me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that...
[SPEAKER_01]: If you still recognize that it doesn't matter how powerful somebody is trying to push through the gate, all I need to do is stay at the gate.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't need to fight them where they are, or chase them inside.
[SPEAKER_01]: I just need to stay at the gate.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you just need to stay at the level of the theme of kindness, and you will then... And, again, that can only be developed if you keep doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you keep practicing it, then you develop confidence in it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: If someone...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you protect that mind of kindness, which now you've been maintaining for a while, someone comes to insult you,
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't have to worry about what your response will be.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because it will come from that place of where you are always situated.
[SPEAKER_00]: If that mind is clear.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you've not lost sight of that mind of kindness.
[SPEAKER_01]: And... And losing sight, just to add, means muddling the knowledge.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not losing... because sometimes people will say lose sight or don't lose sight means I must think about it, I must attend it, attend it, attend it.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Losing sight means being unclear about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, just have to re-clarify.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's always something that I can't quite attend to.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's always, it can only ever be.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not on the level of your sight-sight, which is on the level of your attention.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's also like, it's different than having certain techniques, like,
[SPEAKER_02]: It's trying to rebuild the context through emulating things that you would think be coming out of that context.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, a non-angry person would speak like this.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you don't know that because you're already angry.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, a non-angry person would speak how?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, why don't I remove my anger and then whichever way I speak will be a non-angry way of speaking.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: And others might be witness to you and then start writing down all the things that you do when you respond.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: He says this.
[SPEAKER_02]: He asks the person that.
[SPEAKER_02]: And create a new technique.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, called non-violence.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: They might even disapprove.
[SPEAKER_01]: They'll say, no, that's not how a non-angry person would speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like that what's happened in the suttas with the arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Who was fully enlightened, but was upsetting people.
[SPEAKER_00]: They say, I saw you got angry there, so you're obviously not going to lie.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, people just assumed that he was angry.
[SPEAKER_01]: They just assumed he was angry because he was speaking in such a harsh manner.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, they call him, send him to the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_01]: The Buddha
[SPEAKER_01]: Started talking to himself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, no, he's an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like how you're speaking.
[SPEAKER_01]: And often, there are then, sort of, they're like... they're holy life companions in the holy life that are pleasing to listen, pleasing to sort of be with.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're so friendly, so kind, so... so generous, so helpful with evil wishes, ignorant of the wrong view.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they're the ones they're really hard to live with.
[SPEAKER_01]: They don't speak pleasantly.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're rough around the edges.
[SPEAKER_01]: But they're of the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, the other ones, they're both.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you... the Buddha clearly says which one's more important.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the view.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can... you can...
[SPEAKER_01]: If you can refine your behavior to not upset vast amount of people, great.
[SPEAKER_01]: But don't confuse that to be the practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't confuse that that will somehow regenerate the context that you have no knowledge of.
[SPEAKER_01]: How can that happen?
[SPEAKER_01]: I have no knowledge of the context of absence of ill-will.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, I'm hoping to regenerate it through reading the non-violent communication books and just sort of going through the motion of softly spoken, tailored words.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you just have to learn how to look in a different direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yonis direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: In a more general, in a more encompassing direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: And which is just inquiring into your motivations.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's the... that's the gateway.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why everything, as I said, where we started is converges on action.
[SPEAKER_01]: Convergence of action is basically rooted in motivations.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if it's a good action or a bad action.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not about, oh, I must stop doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, of course, you stop doing things that are against the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, people don't know where to draw a line, and then, whatever, oh, I must stop doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that becomes your form of doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Abstaining from doing everything else, it's what I'm doing all the time, 24-7.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's a very frustrating position to be in.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you realize you can't stop the doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only way to stop the doing is to understand the roots of your action.
[SPEAKER_01]: First, you need to replace the bad doing with good doing, and then get to understand it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But just doing the good will not free you from the nature of action.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, doing the good.
[SPEAKER_02]: Focusing like the... for example, like the non-violent communication technique.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it's all coming... it's all coming based on anger.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why your anger becomes implicit in your practice to be free from anger.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sorry, I'm just...
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't know if this isn't following on exactly what you just said, but from what we were saying before, if you are clear about your motivations, like fully clear, in which case there won't be any delusion in regard to
[SPEAKER_00]: The context that you're in, then, in a sense, you don't need to worry about actions anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no kind of... you don't need to sort of do anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: It becomes effortless because it's absence of action.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, now that's the absence of action.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how you also go beyond doubt as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're unclear about the motivation of your actions, you will be doubting it.
[SPEAKER_01]: If somebody starts questioning it, you'll start doubting it yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it doesn't matter how much you doubt the content.
[SPEAKER_01]: You won't be affected by the doubt towards the content.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're not doubtful in regard to the motivation that made you perform that content in the first place, so you will not be able to doubt it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, maybe I could have done like this or this, but it doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: I know why I've done it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's when people are unclear about that, that's when you just doubt this thing all over you.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's also, it's the end of action.
[SPEAKER_00]: If fully developed, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I mean, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: In case you're not... Because... Because... Because it's just intentions giving rise to all these other intentional actions and that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, there's nothing that needs to be...
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no choice based on ignoring the context that's being made towards those actions, which is what the patujan situation is.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, because, like, yeah, because the patujan is always making individual choices at more... at various particular levels of particularity.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whereas, if it's all guarded right at the top...
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, he's making choices because...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's not aware...
[SPEAKER_01]: that the choices can be made without needing him to be there making them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he's ignoring the general or rather he's unaware, has no clarity in regard to general context.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That means he immediately implies then that he's the sole criteria for making decisions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Failing to see that those decisions can be made only because they were given as... as... as simultaneously arisen options for you to attend and then choose on account of.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, you ignore that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, what else is there making choices?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, it's only me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hence, I am.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hence, I must be.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, choices that he makes are choices rooted in his self-view.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, if you recognize that even I am making this choice, you realize, because in the general context that provided you with these options, you realize it's not rooted in you.
[SPEAKER_01]: The roots of your choice are not rooted in you, which then means the actions that were rooted in your choice cannot be rooted in you either.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, a Pitujana's context is
[SPEAKER_00]: Me.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you can easily see that when you ask yourself what's the context, you always find it as like... it's kind of not me.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like... it's... the context is always prior to...
[SPEAKER_00]: My own particular choices that I make, those choices... Well, that would be true only in case of an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you were to start from a neutral position, that answer is true.
[SPEAKER_01]: But Puthujan is not in a neutral position.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in order for him to arrive at that, that choice is already there, the only way to correctly arrive at it, is to first accept the choices first on him.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, this choice that's on me, is then on what?
[SPEAKER_00]: Hence that acceptance of responsibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: But can't you see that that
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I'm responsible for these particular choices, but those choices are always made within a context that's always already given.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you ask yourself the next question.
[SPEAKER_01]: This seems to be clear to me, I seem to have understood it, and we're completely free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: If the answer is no, means you haven't fully understood it, there is still appropriation of action, means there is still absence of arahantship.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, I'm not denying that there are different degrees of understanding this, but you shouldn't stop short until you're completely beyond it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, since we're back on to sort of like where the... how this is done on a practical level, say that... see, like saying where your motivation is when it comes to an action,
[SPEAKER_03]: You have to have a degree of awareness, wholesome and unwholesome, to say, this is right, this is... Yeah, yeah, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, see, everybody has a degree of that awareness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, you can then refine it even further.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everybody knows what's bad to do with your body.
[SPEAKER_01]: To kill, to steal, to cheat, to lie, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, everybody knows that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Certainly, everyone who is practicing the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, sure, without compromising on that principle, you can start refining it further.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, doesn't the Buddha say, you know, samādhi, citta, only the harious advocate knows the whole thing?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no, he understands the roots of it, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it doesn't mean the puṭṭhujana has no knowledge of what virtue is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he has some sense of something being right, something wrong, but he hasn't actually got the proper...
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly, virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: He has a sense of virtue.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: The point I was sort of, like, I was getting at is that, like, even for the sense of virtue, like, even if you say you have doubts about sense of virtue to a certain degree of some aspect of it or another, and, like, in order to develop that, you sort of start with, eh, not sure what the exact translation is, hīryo tattva.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hmm.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that usually translates as sense of shame and fear of wrongdoing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, fear of wrongdoing and sense of shame already implies a degree of action, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_03]: Like... Like... What do you mean?
[SPEAKER_03]: Like... See, like, it implies virtue, as in, like, a sense of virtue, as in, you know... Well, it implies fear of unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, but...
[SPEAKER_03]: The practicality of it is that the fear of wrongdoing, it's sort of like you have a certain awareness of where your action is rooted.
[SPEAKER_03]: What action?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like any action, like... Well, it's a... it's a context for your actions.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a context for abstaining from wrong actions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Developing fear of wrongdoing means in developing context of not acting unwholesomely, because you have fear of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, out of the fear of wrongdoing, then your actions won't be as unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's a context for your actions and for absence of particular other unwholesome actions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Otherwise, you wouldn't be abstaining from unwholesome actions if you don't have fear of wrongdoing.
[SPEAKER_01]: You would just be doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why are you not doing it then?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why are you practicing restraint?
[SPEAKER_01]: Ah, because you develop fear of non-restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you recognize that to be the basis for the right practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, like, why do I want to practice?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, well, because I want to be free from suffering and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, that's why it's useful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not like go around neurotically and fear everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: What have I done?
[SPEAKER_01]: Was this wholesome?
[SPEAKER_01]: Was this unwholesome?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's recognizing that things rooted in lust, aversion, distraction are unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you value absence of those unwholesome things so much that you fear the possibility of their presence.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you're afraid of their presence,
[SPEAKER_01]: It would be impossible for you to act towards them.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you lose the fear of their possibility, then, yeah, you start getting closer and you start acting towards it.
[SPEAKER_03]: And to refine your awareness of your actions as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: To basically refine your abstinence from unwholesome actions.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then abstinence of unwholesome actions means abstinence from perpetuation of unwholesome principles of craving, lust and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: And now that you're not perpetuating them, they start fading.
[SPEAKER_01]: And once they sort of thin out, you can see through them much better.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's another thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, if there's something... Say there's like a mad rabbit dog on the other side of the gate.
[SPEAKER_01]: And now you know the risks, the implications of that kind of animal.
[SPEAKER_01]: You fear it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You wouldn't go near it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You make sure the gate is boarded.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You've done your bit and you feel safe where you are.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you have a fear of that which is on the other side in case you get there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you make sure you don't get there.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I imagine you don't have that context of that fearful animal.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, I'm quite curious about this dog.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let me go and see.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you make all these actions that result exposing you to that thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which you could have prevented if you develop fear properly, in regard to a proper thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why, like, the the way we encourage monks to sort of contemplate sensuality heights, provides little satisfaction, much greater danger.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if a presence of sensual object is seen implicitly dangerous,
[SPEAKER_01]: You won't have to... oh, now I have to pull my mind back from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your mind already won't be there, because it's dangerous.
[SPEAKER_01]: Lacking the perceptions of danger, yeah, the mind will start detaining it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it causes a sense of shame, fear of wrongdoing.
[SPEAKER_02]: It kind of signals that you're going in the direction...
[SPEAKER_02]: They go very far.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which is going against what you are trying to maintain.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I'm trying to maintain a mind of loving-kindness, and now I'm going to go and beat someone up.
[SPEAKER_02]: I feel uneasy, I feel shameful, as the signal going off, that you're going against that.
[SPEAKER_01]: That signal will be more powerful when there is a greater discrepancy that you were about to create with your action.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, the closer you get, the closer it gets.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, somebody who's been practicing sense-restraint,
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how you also get to increase hīrīyānottapa.
[SPEAKER_01]: You start valuing absence of sensuality more, and the more you do it, the more you value it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So now, the prospect of doing it requires even greater discrepancy of your action to reach that further away, and which means then that the alarm will be much higher.
[SPEAKER_01]: As if somebody who just yesterday decided to give it up, tomorrow he might feel a bit bad, but he doesn't feel the full weight of the danger of giving back into those things.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like a buffer zone.
[SPEAKER_01]: Alarm!
[SPEAKER_01]: And the more you practice, the bigger it is, which means the less likely is that you're going to cross it without becoming aware of what you're about to do.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's what they call the guardians, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, the guardians of the world.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like, yeah, you become more sensitive to... you feel shame in taking sugar.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Seeing the danger in the slightest fault, as the suttas would say.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't mean you become neurotic.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sometimes it might happen as a side effect, but you can grow out of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it means actually maintaining that context.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even any significant thing, such as taking extra sugar, that's offered.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not breaking any rules.
[SPEAKER_01]: But why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because I just have pure craving, desire for sweetness, sweet taste.
[SPEAKER_01]: No physical purpose, no physical necessity or benefit, nutritional benefit.
[SPEAKER_01]: I simply want this taste.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you use that as a criteria to not act, then you would be ashamed when you're about to act.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what it means, like, seeing the danger in the slightest fault.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not like, oh, well, look, look, look, see, this room is this, and you folding a sitting cloth, that's an offense, that's an offense, see, that's a fault.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it means recognizing where the faults are.
[SPEAKER_01]: When things are rooted in greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if on paper, the vinaya says, yes, you can have all the sugar you want, because it's offered.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will still feel ashamed, because you don't need it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And yet, you take it for pure sensual satisfaction.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why, from that attitude, that point of view, there are no loopholes in vinaya.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there are no loopholes to craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if people just follow the letter of the rule, then the millions of rūpas... Oh, well, see, the Buddha didn't specify this, means I can do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whether you can do it or not, should not be rooted in whether it was written or said by the Buddha, should be rooted... Is it rooted in my greed, aversion, delusion?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, then you shouldn't be doing it.
[SPEAKER_02]: New rule.
[SPEAKER_01]: Here we go.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just make that rule.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's, well, again, what Buddha said there is this...
[SPEAKER_01]: He said, oh, I can't keep all these hundred-something rules.
[SPEAKER_01]: The monk comes to the Buddha and says
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't do anything unwholesome by body, by speech, by mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not necessarily sort of a vinaya issue, is it?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just more...
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you have no context whatsoever, you need this formulated vinaya to create that absolute outer edges of the boundary.
[SPEAKER_01]: By you taking that to be the goal in itself,
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why you never actually get to understand where those actions are rooted and where the problem is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's basically just like rounding up the symptoms.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like you can't... like you can't spend your whole life being extremely strict and keeping vinaya.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of course.
[SPEAKER_00]: But not be paying any attention to...
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether what I'm doing is wholesome or unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, so... And that's how you're affected by your own vinaya.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, so, it can still protect you to an extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's still better than being unrestrained.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But still, you need to make that step.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it's true.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like training wheels.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: In a boundary, I think.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's why you can go beyond sīla.
[SPEAKER_01]: Acting unwholesomely is not...
[SPEAKER_01]: sīla, your virtue and sensory strain, does not prevent the root of unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: It just prevents the expression of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like you got sick, you caught some bacteria, that now you have, I don't know, fever as a result of it, and all these other symptoms.
[SPEAKER_01]: And now, on account of those symptoms, you keep aggravating your situation further.
[SPEAKER_01]: You go and jump in a cold pool,
[SPEAKER_01]: To cool down your fever, which actually makes your bacteria even worse.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you don't know that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just deal what you see in front of you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the first thing you have to do is stop jumping in the cold pool that will aggravate your fever, that will help your fever, but aggravate the cause of the fever.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you start practicing restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: Control the symptoms.
[SPEAKER_01]: But now, if you think that all you have to do is abstain from going out into the cold water, because it won't aggravate the fever, and you think that would be enough to then uproot the root cause of the fever as well, that's not going to happen.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, vinaya and sīla is that outer edges who basically, okay, don't aggravate the aggravated symptoms anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: Stop here.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you think that stopping there will also then clear you of the symptoms, that won't happen.
[SPEAKER_01]: Only uprooting the cause will then remove the symptoms.
[SPEAKER_01]: Same like the...
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know why I'm complicating with a different simile.
[SPEAKER_01]: Simile of the itch, the wounds on your skin that they would get.
[SPEAKER_01]: First thing, you have to stop scratching.
[SPEAKER_01]: Scratching will not uproot the bacterial infection.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sorry, eh... cessation of scratching will not uproot the bacterial infection, but it will certainly stop spreading it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you can apply medicine for the underlying cause of that which made you itch in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's basically the vinaya.
[SPEAKER_01]: Stops you from making things worse.
[SPEAKER_01]: But taking that to be a practice for uprooting it, well, that's extremely wrong view.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a first fetter.
[SPEAKER_01]: And unless you abandon it, you won't get the right view, let alone free yourself from lust and aversion later on.
[SPEAKER_03]: Say, if you're confused about where my action is, you can always know in regards to the virtue, as in, I'm not doing this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can be confused in terms of, on a more particular level.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, is this resistant?
[SPEAKER_01]: But, okay, overall, is this wholesome or unwholesome?
[SPEAKER_01]: If it's not unwholesome, then okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Wait and you might get clarity in regard... like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Am I taking... like, there's nothing wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not stealing this sugar.
[SPEAKER_01]: But am I taking it because I really need it, because I really, like, didn't have enough calories, or I'm taking it purely for pleasure's sake?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, as I said, if you're unsure, then don't do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: As a rule of thumb.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know if what I'm about to do...
[SPEAKER_01]: I know it's not unwholesome to the level of breaking rules and so on,
[SPEAKER_01]: But on a more personal level, on a more immediate level, I'm not sure whether it's desire or without desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, don't do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: If there is a disagreeable experience in regard to it, means desire was involved.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you generally then don't care, means there was no desire involved.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you wouldn't be affected by saying no to things, unless you had like a desirous mind towards them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you're doubting, it's most likely rooted in desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hence, doubt is an unwholesome thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not in the sense, I must stop doubting.
[SPEAKER_01]: I must stop thinking.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: I must clarify my mind to go beyond this doubt, so the doubt cannot enter it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't control the doubt.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doubt is another symptom.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's rooted in lack of clarity.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when I say clarity, it means lack of... lack of clarity means lack of understanding, not lack of information.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because sometimes people... yeah, sometimes you don't know enough, so you read the rules and so on, but sometimes people, that's all they do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just need to keep re-reading and be told the same thing, on and on and on and on, to help them deal with the doubt.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's not dealing with the doubt, that's just feeding it further.
[SPEAKER_01]: You want external authority to remove the doubt for you, because you're not seeing for yourself where your actions are rooted.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's why practically you can check that general context, what you're about to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it clearly unwholesome?
[SPEAKER_01]: Then it's non-negotiable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, I want to go for a walk.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it because I'm restless?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or because I need some exercise?
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're unclear, well, then perhaps wait.
[SPEAKER_01]: Decide, no, I won't go for a walk.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do I feel affected now, emotionally, if I have to stay here?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, okay, so then I probably wasn't trying to resist any restlessness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then you can go for a walk.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the only method you can really do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just keep questioning whatever you're about to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, is this right or wrong?"
[SPEAKER_01]: or something like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just, where is it rooted?
[SPEAKER_01]: Right or wrong has been sort of dealt with on the level of vinaya.
[SPEAKER_01]: But now, it's on a practical level.
[SPEAKER_01]: Where is it rooted?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the same thing, externally, can sometimes be wholesome, sometimes unwholesome, depending on whether it's rooted in your desire or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's what we were starting with, which is like asking... That's about the same, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why am I doing this?
[SPEAKER_00]: What's my motivation?
[SPEAKER_00]: And not expecting to have the answer immediately.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Discerning it, what's what's already there enduring.
[SPEAKER_01]: If I don't... oh, yeah, it's because of this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: But why am I doing it right now?
[SPEAKER_01]: Where?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is it that motivates me to go and want to go for a walk?
[SPEAKER_01]: I have no particular reason.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Answer that presented itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I have no particular reason.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that non-particular reason, is it possible that's rooted maybe in me feeling uncomfortable in the kuti on my own?
[SPEAKER_01]: Start investigating, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it going to be unwholesome?
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not clear.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is the starting point.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is this lack of clarity rooted in unwholesome?
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, when you realize that you really don't mind, even if somebody says, you know, you can't go for a walk.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you decide not to go for a walk and you're not going to be affected if you have to stay in the kuti, then it's okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, maybe it wasn't rooted in that, then.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or rather, you know it wasn't rooted in that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then you don't need to find...
[SPEAKER_01]: I must find where exactly it's rooted.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: All you need to find is that it's not rooted in unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything else will be fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how you will also avoid psychologizing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because psychologizing will be focusing on providing the content, the reason.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't... you don't need a reason.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just want to make sure that the absence of these reasons are not caused by greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, that's where we began this interrogation.
[SPEAKER_02]: The importance of interrogation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can... like this, of course, it's basically... well, we recorded it, so you get like a reference collected, so people can listen, including ourselves.
[SPEAKER_01]: You listen to it and, ah, okay, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It reminds you how to do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's a practice you should be doing to yourself all the time.
[SPEAKER_01]: So now, when you go, or everyone goes to their own kuti on their own in the afternoon, and sort of, you're about to do something, you... Oh, is this awesome?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, just, okay, I'm about to do this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why am I doing that?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, are there any red flags coming up, shame?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, just checking peripherally if there are red flags, not necessarily trying to interfere or control what you're about to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, again, say you go back to Kuti now, you finish eating and then, I want to go for a walk.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no problem with that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that doesn't mean you should do it immediately by default.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, you ask yourself, why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Where is this action rooted?
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not looking for faults, I'm just looking for clarity.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's rooted in the fact that I'm getting quite sleepy, and I don't want to sleep.
[SPEAKER_01]: Going out in a cold air, in the wind, walking a bit, will certainly wake me up, or at least has a greater chance of waking me up, than if I don't do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's nothing unwholesome about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if it's purely unwholesome reason, because I heard there are people on the road down there, I heard voices, and I just want to see who there was, and maybe talk to people.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then that becomes clearly, oh, that's why you want to do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You realize that's what you're leaning to, that's what you're hoping for.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you're unsure, oh, is it or not?
[SPEAKER_01]: What if I were to go walking in the opposite direction, when I know there is nobody?
[SPEAKER_01]: Will I feel dejected on account of it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Then you realize, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, because I had the desire, basically, to go down to talk to people on the pretext of having a healthy walk.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's nothing like, oh, how do you... You just need to ask yourself and then look and wait for the answer.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because otherwise, you wouldn't have had that thought of going for a walk where the people are, if it wasn't rooted in that motivation.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not... it's... it... Nobody can say, oh, that's beyond me.
[SPEAKER_01]: This practice is beyond me.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it's truly beyond you, means you're incapable of act, acting and intending.
[SPEAKER_01]: And nobody's incapable of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means everybody's incapable of being aware of the motivation of those acts.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if it's unwholesome, don't do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it's wholesome, do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's all you have to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what we've said millions of times.
[SPEAKER_01]: That which you know it's unskillful, abandon it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That which you know it's skillful, cultivate it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what is skillful, unskillful?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's whether it's rooted in greed, aversion, delusion in your mind, or not.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Interrogation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, I must do this.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, and then I practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is your practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Uprooting any, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: uprooting the maintenance of unskillful states of mind that are maintained through the unskillful actions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you can't have unskillful action being performed without the unskillful intention in the mind persisting with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can certainly uproot the unskillful intention in your mind by abstaining from performing unskillful actions with your body and your speech.